A Guide to the Photographs of Virginia Churches, Courthouses, Homes, and Buildings, 1959-1969
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
{Special Collections, University of Virginia Library}
Photographs of Virginia Churches, Courthouses, Homes, and Buildings, 1959-1969
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11494
The collection consists of seven photograph albums.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These albums were purchased by the University of Virginia Library from Jerry N. Showalter, Ivy, Virginia, on April 14, 1999.
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists of seven photograph albums, ca. 1959-1969, containing black and white snapshots of county courthouses (3 volumes), historic homes, inns and other landmarks (3 volumes) and churches (1 volume) all in Virginia, unless otherwise noted. Each photograph is labeled by place and date of building, if known. Several have additional annotations. The only identified people are Dr. Chester Bradley and Mrs. Stewart posing in front of the Ft. Monroe Casemate Museum. Three earlier photographs of the Fountain Hotel, Rustburg, Va., are included.
Contents List
- Red Lion Tavern, corner of Cork and Loudoun Streets, Winchester, Volume I
- Green Plains, Mathews County, built 1795, Volume I
  2 photos
- Green Plains, home of Judge John Rutherfoord on North River, Section of Scalloped Wall, Volume I
- Bellevue, Halifax County, built 1825, Volume I
- Berry Hill, Halifax County, Volume I
- Ritchie House, Tappahannock, built 1750, birthplace of Thomas Ritchie, founder and editor of The Richmond Enquirer, Volume I
- Mill House, near Abrams Delight, Winchester, Volume I
- The Nelson House, York Hall, built in 1740-1741, Yorktown, Volume I
- The Dudley-Diggs House, built 1755-1760, Yorktown, Volume I
- The Diggs House, built 1705, Yorktown, Volume I
- Somerwell House, built before 1707, owned by the Lightfoot family (1716-1783), Volume I
- Shield House, built by Thomas Sessions, ca. 1699, Yorktown, Volume I
- Windsor Castle, home of Arthur Smith, founder of Smithfield, Smithfield, Virginia, Volume I
- Sykes Inn, used as inn as early as 1752, Smithfield, Volume I
- Kerr Place, 1799, Onancock, Volume I
- Union Hill, ca. 1935, Nelson County, Volume I
- Westover, Charles City County, Volume I
- Chelsea, King William County, Volume I
- Romancoke, King William County, Volume I
- Bremo Recess, Fluvanna County, Volume I
- [Niewstead?], Cumberland County, Volume I
- Wales, Dinwiddie County, Volume I
- Violet Bank, Colonial Heights, Volume I
- Ellington, near Doswell, used as a school before and after the Civil War, Volume I
- Monticello, home of Thomas Jefferson, near Charlottesville, Volume I
- Ashlawn, home of James Monroe, near Charlottesville, Volume I
- Shirley, Charles City County, Volume I
- Monacan, home, kitchen, and corn crib, Powhatan County, Volume I
  4 photos
- Archer House, Norfolk, Volume II
- Barrett House, 1752, Smithfield, Volume II
- Bel Air Plantation House, ca. 1670, Charles City County, Volume II
- Collins House, corner of Bute and Botetourt Streets, Norfolk, Volume II
- Admiral Glesson's House, Freemason & Duke Streets, Volume II
- Jacob Hunter House, presently in the Point of Woods housing development, Virginia Beach, Volume II
- Farmhouse called "the Hotel," King and Queen County, Volume II
- Lamb House, 420 Bute Street, [Norfolk], Volume II
- Pleasant Hall, Kempsville, served as headquarters for Lord Dunmore, Volume II
- Myers House, built in 1792, corner of Freemason & Bank Street, Norfolk, Volume II
- Old house across street from Buckingham County courthouse, Volume II
- Whittle House, built in 1791-1793, 227 Freemason Street, Norfolk, Volume II
  3 photos
- Old John L. Roper carriage house, now a restaurant, Bute Street, Norfolk, Volume II
- Petty-Dickson House, built 1852, by William H. Addington, 300 Freemason Street, Norfolk, Volume II
- Richard Taylor House, first appeared on tax books 1869, Norfolk, Volume II
- Grandy House servant quarters & kitchen, Thomas Street, Norfolk, Volume II
- Glebe House of Southwark Parish, built before 1724, Surry County, Volume II
- Bain House, 326 North Street, Portsmouth, Volume II
- Seldon House, 351 Botetourt Street, Norfolk, Volume II
- Cassell House, 108 London Street, Portsmouth, Volume II
- Bilisoly House, built after1797, 801 Court Street, Portsmouth, Volume II
- Blair House, built 1720-1750, 319 Court Street, Portsmouth, Volume II
- Dale-Reed House, built in 1732, 200 Swimming Point Walk, Portsmouth, Volume II
- Collier House, 412 London Street, Portsmouth, Volume II
- Machinist Union, corner of Court and London Streets, Portsmouth, Volume II
- Hill House, built before 1850, 221 North Street, Portsmouth, Volume II
- Peters House, built in 1852, 315 Court Street, Portsmouth, Volume II
- Murdough Residence, built in 1842, 222 Crawford Street, Portsmouth, Volume II
- Watts House, built in 1799, 500 North Street, Portsmouth, Volume II
- Nivison-Ball House, 213 Middle Street, Portsmouth, Volume II
- Warren House, built in 1652 by Thomas Warren, on land given to John Rolfe by Powhatan, Surry County, Volume II
- Red Hill, home and tombs of Patrick & Dorothea Dandridge Henry, Charlotte County, Volume II
- Point of Honor, built in 1805 by Dr. George Cabell, Lynchburg, Volume II
- Large building on grounds of the James City County Courthouse, Williamsburg, Volume II
- Town House, Franklin, Volume II
- Battletown Inn, Berrytown, Volume II
- Hawthorne House, Berrytown, Volume II
- Battlefield of Great Bridge Stone Marker, December 9, 1775, Norfolk, Volume III
- Juvenile Court of Norfolk, formerly the Norfolk Academy, built between 1840 and1850, North Bank Street, Norfolk, Volume III
- Ft. Monroe Casemate Museum, Dr. Chester and Mrs. Stewart, Ft. Monroe, Volume III
- Debtor's Prison, Eastville, Volume III
- Jail on the County Courthouse grounds, King and Queen County, Volume III
- The Tavern, built before 1862, New Kent, Volume III
- Old Hotel, Buckingham, Volume III
- Hanover Tavern, erected in 1723, Hanover, Volume III
- Hopkins Wharf Museum, mercantile building built in 1839, now headquarters for the Eastern Shore branch of the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, Onancock, Volume III
- Halfway House—Route 1 between Richmond and Petersburg, Chesterfield County, Volume III
- Old Jail, Fincastle, Botetourt County, Volume III
- Warren Green Hotel, erected shortly after 1875 on the site of the Morris Tavern, Warrenton, Volume III
- Monument marking the site of the first Christian Church, erected by the Southern Christian Convention in 1927, Surry, Volume III
- Statue of Norweigian Lady, gift from Moss, Norway to Virginia Beach, Volume III
- Monument marking site of McCabe's University School, Petersburg, Volume III
- Pocahontas Basin, Central Park, Petersburg, Volume III
- The Tavern, Heathsville, Volume III
- Norfolk Boat Club at the end of Freemason Street, Volume III
- County Jail, now a museum, Palmyra, Volume III
- County Jail, built in 1848, Goochland, Volume III
- Old Masonic Hall, built in 1824, Madison, Volume III
- Masonic Hall, formed in 1757, chartered in 1773, Botetourt Lodge No. 7, Gloucester, Volume III
- Hotel Botetourt, Gloucester, Volume III
- Fountain Hotel, Rustburg, Volume III
- Side entrance of the University of Virginia [the Old Hospital], Volume III
- Debtor's Prison, built in 1754, Gloucester, Volume III
- Seneca Mill Foundations, Campbell County, Volume III
- Covered Bridge, near Marysville, Campbell County, Volume III
- Fort Stephens, frontier fort built in 1752, about twelve miles from Winchester, Volume III
- Library of Fairfax, Volume III
- Seawell's Ordinary on route 17, circa 1712, Gloucester County, Volume III
- Old Jail on Court House Square, Chesterfield, Courthouse, Volume III
- Swift Creek Mill, 1663, Chesterfield County, Volume III
- Fountain Hotel, Rustburg, Volume III
- Old Mill at Raphine, Volume III
- Spring Mill, Appomattox County, Volume III
- Old Bay Line [ship], leaving Norfolk, Volume III
- North Landing River Ferry, Pungo, old Princess Anne County, Volume III
- Gray Apartments, Poindexter Street, South Norfolk, Volume III
- Fountain Hotel, Rustburg, Volume III
- Michie Tavern, built before 1740, Albemarle County, Volume III
- Abingdon Church, built 1754, near Gloucester, Volume IV
- Antioch Baptist Church, rebuilt 1895, Saluda, Volume IV
- Bank Street Baptist Church, Norfolk, Volume IV
- Benn's [Methodist] Church, Bishop Ashbury preached there in 1804, Volume IV
- Bruington Church, built in 1851, Baptist church founded in 1780, King and Queen County, Volume IV
- Presbyterian Church, Fincastle, Volume IV
- Cat-tail Church, King William County, Volume IV
- Christ Church, near Eastville, built 1826, Volume IV
- Old Christ Church, Freemason Street, built in 1829, sold to Greek Orthodox Church in 1910, sold to Daddy Grace in 1955, Norfolk, Volume IV
- Eastern Shore Chapel, built in 1754, rebuilt in 1954, Oceana, Volume IV
- El Bethel Church, Amherst County, Volume IV
- Brandon Church, built in 1852, parish founded in 1616, Prince George County, Volume IV
- Emmanuel Church, near Port Royal, on route 301, Volume IV
- Emmanuel Episcopal Church, Port Conway, Prince George County, Volume IV
- Falling Spring Church, dedicated 1864, Rockbridge County, Volume IV
- Hugenot Memorial Window, First Presbyterian Church, Lynchburg, Volume IV
- Fork Church, built in 1735, near where the North Anna and South Anna Rivers meet, Doswell, Volume IV
- Freemason Street Baptist Church, built in 1840, Norfolk, Volume IV
- Glebe Church, built in 1738, Driver, Volume IV
- Grace Episcopal Church, built in 1831, Berryville, Volume IV
- Jerusalem Christian Church, King William County, Volume IV
- Lebanon Presbyterian Church, built in 1747, near Crozet, between Waynesboro and Charlottesville, Volume IV
- Lynnhaven Parish House, oldest part built before 1762, Princess Anne County, Volume IV
- Walls of Lawne's Creek Church, near Surry, Volume IV
- Lower Methodist Church, built 1717 as second chapel of Christ Church Parish, bought for Methodist Church in 1857, near Saluda, on route 33, Volume IV
- Mattapony Church, used by Baptists since 1824, Volume IV
- Manakin Episcopal Church, monument, fourth church built in 1894, and new one built in 1954, modeled after William Byrd's Westover Church, Powhatan County, Volume IV
- Merchant's Hope Church, completed in 1657, Prince George County, Volume IV
- Nimmo Methodist Church, established in 1791, Princess Anne County, Volume IV
- North Farnham Church, built ca. 1737, Richmond County, Volume IV
- Old Church, built in 1720, King and Queen County, Volume IV
- Oak Grove Methodist Church, Chesapeake, Volume IV
- Old Donation Church, built 1733, Lynnhaven, Volume IV
- Perrow's Chapel, Campbell County, Volume IV
- Piedmont Episcopal Church, built in 1834, Madison, Volume IV
- St. James Episcopal Church, King William County, Volume IV
- St. John's Church, parish established 1642, built in 1755, Chuckatuck, Volume IV
- St. John's Church, built in 1732, near King William, Volume IV
- St. John's Church, Warsaw, Volume IV
- St. Stephen's Episcopal Church, Heathsville, Volume IV
- Salem Baptist Church, congregation organized in 1802, Sparta, Volume IV
- St. Stephen's Baptist Church, built in 1842, St. Stephen's Church Community, Volume IV
- St. Paul's Episcopal Church, Lynchburg, Volume IV
- Shrine of the Infant Jesus of Prague, Waverly, Volume IV
- Tabernacle Methodist Church, [built in] 1830, Old Princess Anne County, Volume IV
- Vauter's Church, built in 1719, Essex County on route 17, Volume IV
- Ware Church, parish founded in 1650, built before 1723, Gloucester County, Volume IV
- Westover Episcopal Church, erected in 1737, Charles City County, Volume IV
- Accomac County Courthouse, built in 1890, Volume V
- Amherst County Courthouse, Amherst, Volume V
- Albemarle County Courthouse, Charlottesville, started in 1803, Volume V
- Alleghany County Courthouse, built in 1911, Covington, Volume V
- Augusta County Courthouse, Staunton, Volume V
- Arlington County Courthouse, Arlington, Volume V
- Amelia County Courthouse, Amelia, Volume V
- Alexandria Court House, Volume V
- Bland County Courthouse, Bland, Volume V
- Bedford County Courthouse, Bedford, Volume V
- Buckingham County Courthouse, Volume V
- Bristol City Courthouse, Volume V
- Buena Vista City Courthouse, Volume V
- Brunswick County Courthouse, built about 1854, Lawrenceville, Volume V
- Bath County Courthouse, built 1908, Warm Springs, Volume V
- Botetourt County Courthouse, built 1850 and burned in 1970, Fincastle, Volume V
- Campbell County Courthouse, Rustburg, Volume V
- Charles City County Courthouse, built in 1730, Volume V
- Chesterfield County Courthouse, built in 1917, and the Old Clerk's Office, built in 1828, Chesterfield, Volume V
- Clarke County Courthouse, built in 1840, Berryville, Volume V
- Clifton Forge Courthouse, Clifton Forge, Volume V
- Caroline County Courthouse, built in 1803-1809, Bowling Green, Volume V
- City of Chesapeake Courthouse, built in 1962, during the merger of Norfolk County and the City of South Norfolk, forming Chesapeake, Volume V
- Culpeper County Courthouse, built in 1870, Culpeper, Volume V
- Colonial Heights Municipal Building, Colonial Heights, Volume V
- Cumberland County Courthouse, built in 1818, Cumberland, Volume V
- Dinwiddie County Courthouse, Dinwiddie, Volume V
- Essex County Courthouse, built in 1848, the Clerk's Office built in 1750, & the Old Jail, Tappahannock, Volume V
- Fairfax County Courthouse, built in 1800, Fairfax, Volume V
- Falls Church Courthouse, Volume V
- Frederick County Courthouse, built in 1840, Winchester, Volume V
- Fredericksburg Courthouse, built in 1852, on Princess Anne Street, Fredericksburg, Volume V
- Fluvanna County Courthouse, built in 1838, Palmyra, Volume V
- Fauquier County Courthouse, built in the mid-19th century, Warrenton, Volume V
- Grayson County Courthouse, Independence, Volume V
- Galax City Courthouse, Volume V
- Greensville County Courthouse, built in 1787, Emporia, Volume V
- Gloucester Courthouse, Old Clerk's Office built in 1821, and Clerk's Office built in 1890, Gloucester, Volume V
- Goochland County Courthouse, built in 1826, Goochland, Volume V
- Greene County Courthouse, built around 1838, Standardsville, Volume V
- Halifax County Courthouse, built in 1832, added on to in 1905, Volume VI
- Hampton City Courthouse, built in 1876, on corner of King and Court Streets, Volume VI
- Highland County Courthouse, built in 1848, Monterey, Volume VI
- Hanover County Courthouse, built in 1733, Volume VI
- Henrico County Courthouse, built in 1896, on corner of 22nd and East Main Streets, Richmond, Volume VI
- Old Isle of Wight County Courthouse, 1750-1800, and Clerk's Office, Smithfield, Volume VI
  5 photos
- House at Isle of Wight County Courthouse, built about 1810 by Major Francis Boykins as a tavern, Volume VI
- James City County Courthouse, third one built in 1967, Williamsburg, Volume VI
- James City County Courthouse, earlier construction, Williamsburg, Volume VI
- King George County Courthouse, built in 1915, King George, Volume VI
- King and Queen County Courthouse, built after the Civil War, King and Queen, Volume VI
- King William County Courthouse, built in 1725, King William, Volume VI
- Loudoun County Courthouse, built in 1894, Leesburg, Volume VI
- Louisa County Courthouse, built in 1905, Louisa, Volume VI
- Lunenburg County Courthouse, built in 1826, Lunenburg, Volume VI
- Lancaster County Courthouse, built in 1800, Lancaster, Volume VI
- Matthews County Courthouse, Matthews, Volume VI
- Middlesex County Courthouse, built in 1694, used as a courthouse from 1742-1852, now the home of Middlesex County Woman's Club and Public Library, Urbanna, Volume VI
- Middlesex County Courthouse, Saluda, Volume VI
- Madison County Courthouse, built in 1829, Madison, Volume VI
- Nansemond County Courthouse, Suffolk, Volume VI
- New Kent County Courthouse, built in 1906, New Kent, Volume VI
- Newport News Courthouse, built in 1949, replacing the red brick building of 1891-1893, Newport News, Volume VI
- Northumberland County Courthouse, built in 1851, Heathville, Volume VI
- Northampton County Courthouse, built in 1899, and a former Clerk's Office, Eastville, Volume VI
- Nottoway County Courthouse, Nottoway, Volume VI
- Norfolk County Courthouse, built in 1842, Portsmouth, Volume VI
- Orange County Courthouse, built in 1858, Orange, Volume VI
- Page County Courthouse, Luray, Volume VII
- Prince Edward County Courthouse, built about 1873, Farmville, Volume VII
- Powhatan County Courthouse, built 1817, Powhatan, Volume VII
- Prince George County Courthouse, Prince George County, Volume VII
- Prince George County Courthouse, Prince George County, Volume VII
- Prince William County Courthouse, built in 1893, Manassas, Volume VII
- Richmond County Courthouse, built 1748-1749, Warsaw, Volume VII
- Rappahannock County Courthouse, built 1871, Little Washington, Volume VII
- Rockbridge County Courthouse, built 1896, Lexington, Volume VII
- Roanoke County Courthouse, Salem, Volume VII
- Scott County Courthouse, Gates City, Volume VII
- South Boston Courthouse, an independent city courthouse, Volume VII
- Shenandoah County Courthouse, built 1791-1792, Woodstock, Volume VII
- Southampton County Courthouse, Courtland, Volume VII
- Stafford County Courthouse, built 1922, Stafford, Volume VII
- South Norfolk Corporation Courthouse, now a part of Chesapeake, South Norfolk, Volume VII
- Spotsylvania County Courthouse, built 1870, Spotsylvania, Volume VII
- Smyth County Courthouse, Marion, Volume VII
- Surry Courthouse Grounds, Old Clerk Office, now a museum, Volume VII
- Surry County Courthouse, Surry, Volume VII
- Sussex County Courthouse, Clerk's Office, Sussex, Volume VII
- Sussex County Courthouse, Sussex, Volume VII
- Virginia Beach Courthouse, Virginia Beach, Volume VII
- Warwick County Courthouse, now the Denbigh Presbyterian Church, Newport News, Volume VII
- Confederate Monument at the old Warwick County Courthouse, Newport News, Volume VII
- Public Library, the old Clerk's Office of Warwick County, built in 1810, Newport News, Volume VII
- Washington County Courthouse, Abingdon, Volume VII
- Wythe County Courthouse, Wytheville, Volume VII
- Waynesboro City Building & Courts, Volume VII
- Warren County Courthouse, built in 1936 on the site of the first one built in 1837, Front Royal, Volume VII
- Westmoreland County Courthouse, Montross, Volume VII
- York County Courthouse, built in 1955 as the fifth courthouse there since 1691, Yorktown, Volume VII